Guide to the Bannerman Family Papers 1788 - 2001 (bulk 1890-1968) MS 2906
New-York Historical Society
Bannerman Family Papers
1788-2001 (bulk 1890-1968)
New-York Historical Society
Bannerman, Francis, VI, 1851-1918
MS 2906
3 Linear feet (7 boxes and 3 volumes)
Francis (Frank) Bannerman VI was born in Dundee, Scotland on March 24, 1851. Following the Civil War, Bannerman founded a company, Francis Bannerman Co., specializing in military surplus and scrap. In 1900 Bannerman puchased Polopel Island, a small island located in the Hudson River just north of West Point, NY, with the aim to turn it into a safe storage location for his large stores of military surplus that had now outgrown his warehouse space in Brooklyn. Patriotic to his heritage, Bannerman designed plans to have a unique, Scottish-style estate be constructed on the island to serve both his business and personal needs. The family owned both the business and the island until the late 1960s. Subseries IV.D Glass Plate Negatives is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Biographical Note
Francis (Frank) Bannerman VI was born in Dundee, Scotland on March 24, 1851. At the age of three he and his family moved to the United States, where they settled in Brooklyn. Soon after, Bannerman's father began a business of re-selling items purchased at Naval auctions. When his father joined the Union Army during the Civil War, Francis carried on and gradually grew the business by collecting large quantities of scrap. Once the Civil War ended, Bannerman officially founded his own company, Francis Bannerman Co., at the age of 14. It was during a business trip to Ireland a few years later, in 1872, that Bannerman met and married his wife, Helen Boyce.
In 1900 Bannerman purchased Polopel Island, a small island located in the Hudson River just north of West Point, NY, with the aim to turn it into a safe storage location for his large store of military surplus that had now outgrown his warehouse space in Brooklyn. Patriotic to his heritage, Bannerman designed plans to have a unique, Scottish-style estate constructed on the island to serve both his business and personal needs. Construction began in 1900 and continued steadily through the time of Bannerman's death in 1918. Buildings constructed included an arsenal, a superintendent's house, a workshop, a powder house, an ice house, breakwaters, turrets and a grand personal residence and gardens for the Bannermans. Proud of his island home, Francis attempted to officially rename the island "Bannerman Island," but never gained consent to do so. During their time living on the island, a number of unfortunate incidents befell the Bannermans, including a large explosion at the powder house in 1920 that caused minor injuries and a fair amount of damage, and frequent lightning strikes due to the castle's numerous flag poles.
In 1918 two of Francis Bannerman's sons, Frank Jr. and David Boyce, became partners in the business and changed its name to Francis Bannerman Sons. When Francis passed away later that year, his two sons carried on and continued to grow the business. In 1946, following the death of Frank Jr., Francis' grandson Charles S. Bannerman became a partner and incorporated the business. In 1959 Charles, then President, closed the company's storefront that had long been on Broadway and moved the business office to Blue Point, Long Island. The family sold the company to James F. Hogan, previously the company's secretary, in the late 1960s.
In 1967 the Bannermans sold Polopel Island to The People of the State of New York, and on July 1, 1968 it was placed under the supervision of the Taconic State Park Commission. Unfortunately, a fire during the night of August 8, 1969 severely damaged all of the buildings. Today the island and the ruins remaining of the buildings are maintained by a non-profit agency associated with the New York State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series, three topical and one based on media format: Bannerman Family, Francis Bannerman (Sons) Business, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, and Photographs and Negatives. Within these series, materials are arranged chronologically. Undated materials have been placed at the end of each series or subseries and are arranged alphabetically.
This collection is organized into the following four series. Within these series, materials are arranged chronologically. Undated materials have been placed at the end of each series or subseries and are arranged alphabetically.
Missing Title
Series I: Bannerman Family
Series II: Francis Bannerman (Sons) Business
Series III: Polopel (Bannerman) Island
Series IV: Photographs and Negatives
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Custodial History
Donated to the New-York Historical Society by Virginia Collins in 2011.
Related Materials
There is a large collection of Bannerman family and business papers at the Hagley Museum and Library. http://www.hagley.lib.de.us/library/collections/manuscripts/bannermanabst.html Contact them for more details.
Scope and Contents
This collection pertains to the personal life, business and estate of Francis Bannerman VI and his family. Primary topics in this collection are the Bannerman family; military equipment and World War I, which are reflective of Bannerman's company's specialty of military surplus and his interest in military achievement; and Polopel (Bannerman) Island and the estate Bannerman built there. Materials include correspondence, notes, time books, scrapbooks, clippings, monographs, serials, photographs, glass plate negatives and objects.
Black-and-white negatives; Hudson River (N.Y. and N.J.) -- History.; Polopel Island; World War, 1914-1918; Scrapbooks.; Photographs.; Correspondence.; Bylaws; Minutes (administrative records); Francis Bannerman (Firm); Francis Bannerman Son; West Point (N.Y.); Bannerman, Francis, VI, 1851-1918
- Series I: Bannerman Family
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials belonging to Francis Bannerman VI and various members of the Bannerman Family. The majority of materials pertain to Francis Bannerman's interest in World War I, the military and Scotland, including primarily clippings, and scrapbooks. Other materials include monographs, serials, mortgages, deeds and mid-nineteenth century stock certificates that could belong to various family members.
  - Vindication of the Clanronald of Glengarry, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stock Certificates, 1853-56 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cornell's Intermediate Geography, [1865] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mortgages, Deeds, Bonds, 1886-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ladies Home Journal, Midsummer 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - New York Tribune, Photographic History of the Great War, vol. I, no. I-IV, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - New York Tribune, Photographic History of the Great War, vol. I, no. V, VI, VIII, IX; vol. 2, no. I, 1914-15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New York Times, 1915, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, "To Francis Bannerman Esq. from the Scottish Company City of London National Guard", 1916 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - New York Tribune, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - History of the Great Iron Chain, and supporting materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Postcard Scrapbook, English - European, vol. 1, undated (Volume 1)
- Series II: Francis Bannerman (Sons) Business
  This series contains materials pertaining to the Bannerman family business, Francis Bannerman (Sons), including correspondence, notes, employee time books, scrapbooks and publications printed by the company.
  - Subseries A: Business Records
    This subseries contains materials pertaining to the Bannerman family business from the 1890s to the 1970s. It includes correspondence, records and notes pertaining to the company's general business, ventures and eventual sale. In particular there are materials relating to its dealings with Lord Kitchnes regarding the Belgian Relief during WWI, the family of Admiral Dewey regarding the USS Olympia, the Marsteller Family regarding donations and relics, and the New York Central Railroad regarding a track crossing agreement.
    - F. Bannerman Sons Correspondence and Documents, 1891-1917 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Employee Time Book, weekly, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Loose Scrapbook Materials from Vol. 2, 1892-93 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - F. Bannerman Business, 1897-1919 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Olympia and Admiral Dewey, 1898-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Francis Bannerman Business Notes, [1900] (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - F. Bannerman Sons, Marstellers, 1903-17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1905-17 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Lord Kitchnes, Belgian Relief, 1914-18, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence [1 of 2], 1915 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence [2 of 2], 1915-17 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Agreement with New York Central Railroad, 1915-68 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Employee Time Book, weekly, 1916-18 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bannerman Family Partnership, [1917] (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Belgian Relief Letters and Checks, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Employee Time Book, Bannerman's Arsenal, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Sale of Estate, 1923-68 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Employee Time Book, weekly, 1929-36 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Quaker Realty Company, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Efforts to Sell the Business, 1946-48 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Bannerman Booth at Congressional Church Antique Show in Manhasset, 1954-56, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Francis Bannerman Sons, 1955-68 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence and Documents, 1956-57 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Francis Bannerman Sons, Inc., 1956-59 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Franics Bannerman Sons, Inc., Bylaws and Minutes, 1957-68 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Binder, Francis Bannerman Sons, Inc., undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
      General
      Originally held Francis Bannerman Sons, Inc., Bylaws and Minutes.
    - Francis Bannerman Sons, 1971-75 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Scrapbook, vol. 2, 1892-93 (Volume 2)
    - Scrapbook, vol. 3, undated (Volume 3)
  - Subseries B: Printed Material
    - Francis Bannerman Sons Catalogs, 1945-55 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Bannerman Military Catalogue, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Bannerman Military Catalogue, 84th Anniversary, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Bannerman Military Catalogue, 90th Anniversary, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Bannerman Military Catalogue, 100th Anniversary, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Francis Bannerman Sons, list of parts and equipment, [1966] (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series III: Polopel (Bannerman) Island
  This series contains materials pertaining to Polopel (Bannerman) Island, of which there are many spellings, and the Bannermans' time living there, including documents, clippings, correspondence and printed materials. Particular events covered include the arrest of Charles Kovac, the island's superintendent, for being an unnaturalized Austrian alien; the occupation of the island in 1918 when a sub-cruiser crew made an unauthorized search of the island; and the island's nomination for the historic register.
  - Deed, Polleples Island (photocopy), 1788 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Blue Print, Island Under Water, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Map of Polopel Island, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Detention of Charlie Kovacs, "Raid" on Island by USN, and Other Notes and Clippings, 1917-18 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Occupation of the Island, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - More Correspondence on Occupation of the Island by Army, 1918-19 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1918-2001 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper and Other Clippings about Bannerman's Island, 1920, 1956-67 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1940, 1956-68 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1961-68 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Story of Bannerman Island, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Calendar Featuring the Island, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Nomination, National Historic Register, 1980-83 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Bannerman Island, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Coat of Arms, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Island Pictures, Selected for the Booklet, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Maps, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Scenes Along the Hudson River, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Coat of Arms, metal, undated (Box 7)
  - Coat of Arms, stamp, undated (Box 7)
- Series IV: Photographs and Negatives
  This series contains photographs, negatives and glass plate negatives of the Bannerman Family, the Francis Bannerman (Sons) business and Polopel (Bannerman) Island.
  - Subseries A: Bannerman Family
    This subseries contains photographs and negatives of members of the Bannerman Family, including Francis Bannerman VI, Helen Boyer Bannerman and David Bannerman Jr.
    - Photographs, 1914, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Photographs, "For the Rhode Island Branch of the Family", undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Negatives, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Subseries B: Francis Bannerman (Sons) Business
    This subseries contains photographs and negatives of the Francis Bannerman (Sons) store on Broadway and various military surplus.
    - Negatives, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Subseries C: Polopel (Bannerman's) Island
    This subseries contains photographs and negatives of Polopel (Bannerman) Island, its structures and daily life while the family lived there.
    - Negatives, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subseries D: Glass Plate Negatives
    This series contains glass plate negatives of Polopel (Bannerman) Island, including images of the interior and exterior of the Bannerman's house and the island itself. A CD of digital prints made from the negatives is also included.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Digital copies are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
    - CD, Digital Prints from Glass Plate Negatives, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Group Picture, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Exterior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Exterior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Exterior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Exterior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Exterior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Exterior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Exterior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Exterior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Exterior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Interior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Interior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, House Interior, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Polopel (Bannerman) Island, undated (Box 7)
    - Glass Plate Negative, Window View, undated (Box 7)